<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Let &#8217;em Talk	</title>
	<atom:link href="/2015/09/11/let-em-talk/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2015/09/11/let-em-talk/</link>
	<description>iteration, making, building, and coding in education</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 09:09:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Clara Maxcy (Cleargrace)		</title>
		<link>/2015/09/11/let-em-talk/#comment-400</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Clara Maxcy (Cleargrace)]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 09:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2296#comment-400</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I love the way you have stated your classroom practice; the way you have managed to remove yourself from the &quot;sage on the stage&quot;. I have found that children enjoy challenging work instead of boring lecture, and your experience with what children are doing as you intro a topic is exactly what I have experienced. For me, one of the hardest parts of getting started was/is deciding what problem to put out there for the discussion. The second difficulty was/is creating the student led group environment. For the former, I choose a complex example of what I need them to be able to solve on their own. For the latter, I ask &quot;why&quot; and &quot;how do you know&quot; to get them started. A few weeks into school, they start telling me how they know without my prompt- and I hear them doing this to each other in their groups--]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I love the way you have stated your classroom practice; the way you have managed to remove yourself from the &#8220;sage on the stage&#8221;. I have found that children enjoy challenging work instead of boring lecture, and your experience with what children are doing as you intro a topic is exactly what I have experienced. For me, one of the hardest parts of getting started was/is deciding what problem to put out there for the discussion. The second difficulty was/is creating the student led group environment. For the former, I choose a complex example of what I need them to be able to solve on their own. For the latter, I ask &#8220;why&#8221; and &#8220;how do you know&#8221; to get them started. A few weeks into school, they start telling me how they know without my prompt- and I hear them doing this to each other in their groups&#8211;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
