<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: When things just work &#8211; starting with computers	</title>
	<atom:link href="/2013/02/05/when-things-just-work-starting-with-computers/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2013/02/05/when-things-just-work-starting-with-computers/</link>
	<description>iteration, making, building, and coding in education</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2013 00:44:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Evan Weinberg		</title>
		<link>/2013/02/05/when-things-just-work-starting-with-computers/#comment-167</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Evan Weinberg]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2013 00:44:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=935#comment-167</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;/2013/02/05/when-things-just-work-starting-with-computers/#comment-166&quot;&gt;dawndup&lt;/a&gt;.

Hi, thanks for commenting.

Mental math definitely has its place. So does algebra. I&#039;ve always bought the argument that full understanding of algebraic procedures comes later because that&#039;s exactly what happened with me in my own classes. I&#039;m one that made it through though, and I don&#039;t think it&#039;s great policy to assume that what worked for me will work for everyone. Moving from abstract to concrete is the more traditional route - teach a concept, practice, and then apply it in a word problem. I think we need to be thinking in the other direction and NOT insist on an algebraic approach as the only &#039;real&#039; way to explore a subject.

The graphing calculator is fascinating. Wireless technology was not built in to them from the beginning, so getting them to network (for good use) in the classroom has always required an external device to handle that communication. With tons of wireless devices now available and capable of so much more than a bulky plastic box with monochrome LCD screen, graphing calculators just look like dinosaurs.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="/2013/02/05/when-things-just-work-starting-with-computers/#comment-166">dawndup</a>.</p>
<p>Hi, thanks for commenting.</p>
<p>Mental math definitely has its place. So does algebra. I&#8217;ve always bought the argument that full understanding of algebraic procedures comes later because that&#8217;s exactly what happened with me in my own classes. I&#8217;m one that made it through though, and I don&#8217;t think it&#8217;s great policy to assume that what worked for me will work for everyone. Moving from abstract to concrete is the more traditional route &#8211; teach a concept, practice, and then apply it in a word problem. I think we need to be thinking in the other direction and NOT insist on an algebraic approach as the only &#8216;real&#8217; way to explore a subject.</p>
<p>The graphing calculator is fascinating. Wireless technology was not built in to them from the beginning, so getting them to network (for good use) in the classroom has always required an external device to handle that communication. With tons of wireless devices now available and capable of so much more than a bulky plastic box with monochrome LCD screen, graphing calculators just look like dinosaurs.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: dawndup		</title>
		<link>/2013/02/05/when-things-just-work-starting-with-computers/#comment-166</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[dawndup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 17:15:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=935#comment-166</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I teach middle school math but I wanted to comment on how much I admire your persistent use of a variety of technology in the classroom.  I agree with the wonderings in your last paragraph, and it&#039;s something I am playing with in my classroom as well.  I strive to find an even balance between hand computation, mental math / estimation, and use of technology.  However I wonder if the balance shouldn&#039;t be more skewed toward mental math &#038; technology and much less toward the hand computation.  
I also wonder about the future of the graphing calculator.  Of course in middle school math, it has less utility than in Algebra II - for the activities we do, an online graphing calculator or smart phone app work beautifully and are much friendlier than a graphing calculator.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I teach middle school math but I wanted to comment on how much I admire your persistent use of a variety of technology in the classroom.  I agree with the wonderings in your last paragraph, and it&#8217;s something I am playing with in my classroom as well.  I strive to find an even balance between hand computation, mental math / estimation, and use of technology.  However I wonder if the balance shouldn&#8217;t be more skewed toward mental math &amp; technology and much less toward the hand computation.<br />
I also wonder about the future of the graphing calculator.  Of course in middle school math, it has less utility than in Algebra II &#8211; for the activities we do, an online graphing calculator or smart phone app work beautifully and are much friendlier than a graphing calculator.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
