<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: Differentiation Rules &#8211; Making it Interactive	</title>
	<atom:link href="/2012/09/27/differentiation-rules-making-it-interactive/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2012/09/27/differentiation-rules-making-it-interactive/</link>
	<description>iteration, making, building, and coding in education</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 08:48:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Shawn Urban (Stefras)		</title>
		<link>/2012/09/27/differentiation-rules-making-it-interactive/#comment-122</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Shawn Urban (Stefras)]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 08:48:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=769#comment-122</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I like the new approach, Evan. I hope it works for your students and you, and look forward to hearing how it went.

I do wish to address your point about copying notes.

As a learner, I can not understand most things I am taught - inside the class and out - unless I take notes. Oral learning really confuses me; I mute my computer unless I am watching a video which depends on audio. Watching an explanation or demonstration of a concept is useless for me as I forget what I watched. Experimentation and doing are just as bad. I learn by taking notes.

These notes don&#039;t necessarily need to be copied, but, when you are hiking on an unfamiliar trail, it is best to follow precisely the map you are given until you become familiar enough with the trail to write notes that are more reflective and perceptive. I write these notes as well. Soon the notes drop away.

You are right. Most of your kids are likely copying notes as a substitute for reasoning. I would not be one of those students. The key here is that I review my notes when I have time to truly explore the concepts and skills they describe. Essentially, I do on my own what others try to get me to do during a lesson. I find the lesson overstimulating to do it then. Most of your kids who are copying notes probably don&#039;t review their notes, at least not before they cram for tests.

Ironically, as a teacher, I try to teach without students copying notes. I strongly believe in reasoning and learning in the moment and through experimentation and exploration. I believe in inquiry and discussion and hands-on experience. I certainly feel that those of my students who spend their time taking notes instead of reasoning and participating are not learning. It is just that I would be one of those students.

Something to consider. Something to plan lessons around maybe.

Have fun with the new approach.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I like the new approach, Evan. I hope it works for your students and you, and look forward to hearing how it went.</p>
<p>I do wish to address your point about copying notes.</p>
<p>As a learner, I can not understand most things I am taught &#8211; inside the class and out &#8211; unless I take notes. Oral learning really confuses me; I mute my computer unless I am watching a video which depends on audio. Watching an explanation or demonstration of a concept is useless for me as I forget what I watched. Experimentation and doing are just as bad. I learn by taking notes.</p>
<p>These notes don&#8217;t necessarily need to be copied, but, when you are hiking on an unfamiliar trail, it is best to follow precisely the map you are given until you become familiar enough with the trail to write notes that are more reflective and perceptive. I write these notes as well. Soon the notes drop away.</p>
<p>You are right. Most of your kids are likely copying notes as a substitute for reasoning. I would not be one of those students. The key here is that I review my notes when I have time to truly explore the concepts and skills they describe. Essentially, I do on my own what others try to get me to do during a lesson. I find the lesson overstimulating to do it then. Most of your kids who are copying notes probably don&#8217;t review their notes, at least not before they cram for tests.</p>
<p>Ironically, as a teacher, I try to teach without students copying notes. I strongly believe in reasoning and learning in the moment and through experimentation and exploration. I believe in inquiry and discussion and hands-on experience. I certainly feel that those of my students who spend their time taking notes instead of reasoning and participating are not learning. It is just that I would be one of those students.</p>
<p>Something to consider. Something to plan lessons around maybe.</p>
<p>Have fun with the new approach.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: kaleb40		</title>
		<link>/2012/09/27/differentiation-rules-making-it-interactive/#comment-121</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kaleb40]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 04:33:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=769#comment-121</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I totally agree, it&#039;s so hard to find the balance between what you want to prove and what you need them to just accept. You can&#039;t prove everything. Also, what do you have them try to discover is a challenge to figure out as well. I liked your worksheet, it has some problem types that reminded me I need to be intentional about teaching because they re not in my book.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I totally agree, it&#8217;s so hard to find the balance between what you want to prove and what you need them to just accept. You can&#8217;t prove everything. Also, what do you have them try to discover is a challenge to figure out as well. I liked your worksheet, it has some problem types that reminded me I need to be intentional about teaching because they re not in my book.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
