<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>
	Comments on: New Moves: Reassessment	</title>
	<atom:link href="/2017/12/15/new-moves-reassessment/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2017/12/15/new-moves-reassessment/</link>
	<description>iteration, making, building, and coding in education</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2017 20:58:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.6</generator>
	<item>
		<title>
		By: Evan Weinberg		</title>
		<link>/2017/12/15/new-moves-reassessment/#comment-523</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Evan Weinberg]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2017 20:58:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2802#comment-523</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In reply to &lt;a href=&quot;/2017/12/15/new-moves-reassessment/#comment-522&quot;&gt;Andy &quot;SuperFly&quot; Rundquist&lt;/a&gt;.

Realizing that the true value you get out of a project is the satisfaction of completing it is an important step in the process.

Thanks for sharing, Andy.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In reply to <a href="/2017/12/15/new-moves-reassessment/#comment-522">Andy &#8220;SuperFly&#8221; Rundquist</a>.</p>
<p>Realizing that the true value you get out of a project is the satisfaction of completing it is an important step in the process.</p>
<p>Thanks for sharing, Andy.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Andy "SuperFly" Rundquist		</title>
		<link>/2017/12/15/new-moves-reassessment/#comment-522</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Andy "SuperFly" Rundquist]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 12:56:56 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2802#comment-522</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thanks for the honest description of why you stepped away from a project. I found myself nodding my head as you talked about how you realized there was another way, even if it was one you might not be as proud of (I don&#039;t mean you&#039;d be embarrassed by the other one, just that you had something that you created on your own that gave you joy, and now needed to use something else that worked great but you couldn&#039;t claim that you invented it). I face decisions like that all the time. Earlier this week I spent 2 days making cool visuals of how students change majors at my institution. On the third day I showed it to a colleague and he said, &quot;oh, just like this report from EAB (our data management partner)&quot;. I realized that the EAB system is much better suited for others to play with the data and I realized that I hadn&#039;t even looked around when first starting my version of the project. I know why. It was because it was fun and I figured others would appreciate it and me. So anyways, thanks for this great insight into how you dealt with a similar situation.]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for the honest description of why you stepped away from a project. I found myself nodding my head as you talked about how you realized there was another way, even if it was one you might not be as proud of (I don&#8217;t mean you&#8217;d be embarrassed by the other one, just that you had something that you created on your own that gave you joy, and now needed to use something else that worked great but you couldn&#8217;t claim that you invented it). I face decisions like that all the time. Earlier this week I spent 2 days making cool visuals of how students change majors at my institution. On the third day I showed it to a colleague and he said, &#8220;oh, just like this report from EAB (our data management partner)&#8221;. I realized that the EAB system is much better suited for others to play with the data and I realized that I hadn&#8217;t even looked around when first starting my version of the project. I know why. It was because it was fun and I figured others would appreciate it and me. So anyways, thanks for this great insight into how you dealt with a similar situation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>
		By: Clara		</title>
		<link>/2017/12/15/new-moves-reassessment/#comment-521</link>

		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Clara]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 10:35:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=2802#comment-521</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I am chunking content in my Alg 1 class b/c of learning issues. I want to make sure that I give the kids ways to see the content and have an opportunity to show progress. I have not used quizzes as extensively as each standard, but I think this will be something I will build into next semester to help my kids see where they are... I want them to be more successful on their tests, which my district grading system weights at over 50% of grade (across district/summative assessments). They need a better way to see where they are academically. We are also using google for ed and I love the calendar functionality!]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am chunking content in my Alg 1 class b/c of learning issues. I want to make sure that I give the kids ways to see the content and have an opportunity to show progress. I have not used quizzes as extensively as each standard, but I think this will be something I will build into next semester to help my kids see where they are&#8230; I want them to be more successful on their tests, which my district grading system weights at over 50% of grade (across district/summative assessments). They need a better way to see where they are academically. We are also using google for ed and I love the calendar functionality!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
